Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Your Highness gained a lot of favor today.
The Empress looked frumpy sitting next to you.
Although His Majesty encourages frugality,
the imperial family would lose face if I dress modestly.
Who doesn't like to have their women looking radiant next to them?
I was thinking that Her Majesty the Empress Dowager is still unwell...
I should send her something to show my filial piety.
It will also lift Her Majesty's spirits.
That's easy. No expense is too great for a worthy present.
How much money is left from the gifts given by the people I introduced to my brother?
I went through the account books just now.
There are still over four thousand taels left
after sending out rewards and purchasing jewelry.
That's not enough.
I have to send Her Majesty the best or nothing.
If only I could get more funds right now.
Zhou Ninghai said there's someone who has long desired to make your Highness' acquaintance.
Who is he?
Zhao Zhiyuan, the official who was denounced by
the great general and dismissed last month.
No.
My brother personally spoke against him to his Majesty.
How can I let him meet my brother?
Zhao Zhiyuan said if he can have a word with the great general,
he will send fifty thousand taels to Your Highness.
He will double the amount if he succeeds.
All right, tell Zhou Ninghai to take
his money and pass forward his name.
I'll see if how persuasive he is.
Peace to Great General Nian.
His Majesty is playing Go with Noble Prince Guo.
I'll wait here.
Yes, thank you for your patience, Great General.
May I trouble you to move to the side, sir?
Officials cannot stand in the middle.
I won't be here for very long.
Yes.
Go get a chair for the great general.
Great General, please take a seat.
Move it a bit forward.
Move a little closer.
Great general, please sit down.
How was your trip to Sichuan?
The scenery was beautiful but the people were cold.
I traveled all the way to the west to Shaanxi and Gansu.
The people there showed absolute obedience to General Nian .
All the occasional dissenters had been suppressed quickly.
You won the game.
I only narrowly squeaked by.
I fought hard, but still "lost the full board".
I shouldn't have overestimated my "liberties" [Go terminology].
What's the point of winning easily?
It is more interesting to plan painstakingly and finally succeed.
I can't match you at Go.
Go, just like governance, is about checks and balances.
I only know about "invade and defense" but not balance.
No wonder I lose every time.
This is it for the game.
I will seek more advice from you next time.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
Great General Nian.
Peace to Your Lordship.
After living in the northwest for years,
my legs ache in cold weather.
I'm afraid I cannot stand up and bow to Your Lordship properly.
I seek Your Lordship's forgiveness .
It's all right.
Just make sure you show proper manners to His Majesty.
What's wrong?
Your Lordship has a good temper, but I don't.
I cannot bear to see Your Lordship being offended.
All officials had to kneel upon his arrival.
You can tell how much power and influence he holds from that.
He and Long Keduo are like
His Majesty's "left and right hands".
I'm just a son of the prior Emperor.
Not anyone important to His Majesty.
But Your Lordship is a titled lord,
therefore he is your a servant.
A lord out of grace is less than a servant.
And a servant in power can lord over the master.
Ever since His Majesty acceded to the throne,
he has been very cautious of all of the lords.
To me, he has been caring and considerate.
But Nian Gengyao is so domineering.
I can't tolerate it.
Unobtrusiveness and self-restraint is
the way to survive in His Majesty's court.
But...
That's enough.
Your Lordship, are we visiting the Consort Dowager
[the Prince's mother] at the end of this month?
Is everything ready?
Yes, Your Lordship, the same as usual.
I restrain myself for my mother's well-being,
and she does the same for me.
- Talk no more of it, A-Jin.
- Yes.
I am guilty of misleading Your Majesty due to my poor judgement.
I entreat Your Majesty's forgiveness.
What happened? Rise and answer me.
Yes.
I reported to Your Majesty that the Governor of Zhili, Zhao Zhiyuan, was incompetent and making poor decisions.
He was suspended pending investigation because I believed unfounded rumors.
After thoroughly investigating his work,
I discovered instead that he is loyal and competent.
My mistake caused Zhao Zhiyuan to be unfairly dismissed.
I have been reflecting on it in deep remorse
and have come to seek Your Majesty's punishment.
You were making a judgement on my behalf.
Since you had to attend to everything personally it's understandable that this was overlooked.
Since he has already been suspended ...
If a loyal official like Zhao Zhiyuan is not engaeed by Your Majesty's court,
it would be on my conscience when I eat and sleep.
I have already dismissed him based on your advice.
If I were to flip-flop on this decision and reinstate him,
I'm afraid my words would carry less conviction in the future.
This is an error of my own making.
If it causes Your Majesty to lose a
reputable official, I cannot assuage my guilty conscience.
Your Majesty has already discharged him as a governor,
But what if he was appointed to another position?
For one thing, it saves face for Your Majesty.
For another, it saves a loyal servant to Your Majesty.
Do you... insist?
I have made a mistake.
I must not make another one.
I beg Your Majesty to allow me to make amends.
If you insist, I will make an exception and retain his services.
What position do you think I should give him?
I am too humble to make a decision for Your Majesty.
You know his strengths. I believe you will make a better judgement.
Zhao Zhiyuan is qualified to be the
Review Director of the Ministry of Public Works.
[in charge of official communication and public grievance]
I will take your advice.
I thank Your Majesty.
You have been more than loyal to the country, devoting your mind and your heart.
I see you as the backbone of the nation.
I bow to Your Majesty in humble gratitude.
Please pardon my ignorance of your name, My Lady.
Nian Gengyao bows in respect to you.
This is Noble Lady Sourire.
Noble Lady Sourire?
Peace to Great General Nian.
Thank you, My Lady.
Consort Fleur is my sister.
Peace to Her Highness is peace to myself.
Her Highness is in high favor and hence in peace.
Although she's in His Majesty's favor,
I'm afraid she might be offended by someone conceited
about their status and impertinent to their superior.
I can't imagine anyone would "make trouble out of nothing".
I do hope so.
Otherwise, I will step in for Her Highness
even if His Majesty doesn't.
Brother and sister care for each other.
If you understand that, My Lady,
I shall take my leave.
How did Nian Gengyao look when he went out?
The great general looked even more
delighted than when he arrived.
He looked very proud to be summoned by Your Majesty.
So he did.
Your Majesty was playing Go with
Lord XVII when the great general arrived.
So the great general took a seat outside to wait.
He was sitting?
Ah, yes, he was.
And, even when His Lordship went out,
the great general remained seated.
He explained it was because of his injury.
It was good that Lord XVII has a good temper.
His Lordship didn't take offence.
After all, who would take offence from the most honored general?
Perhaps I misspoke.
You were being truthful.
Aiyo.
- Mr Su.
- Peace to Lady Sourire.
I was going to send a sedan chair
for you to come over, My Lady.
I am flattered.
- Is His Majesty here?
- Yes.
Great General Nian visited.
He didn't get into His Majesty's good graces.
Your Lady should be mindful of this.
Thank you, sir.
Open the door.
I bow before Your Majesty.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
Yes.
Sit.
Did I come at a bad time?
Your Majesty must be feeling a bit tired after
the meeting with Great General Nian.
I do.
Huan Huan, you are very well-read.
What do you think of political factions?
I should not pass comments on state affairs.
Don't worry. We will talk only about history.
I know little about it as a concubine in the harem.
But I deeply sympathize with
the Proposition on Factions by Ouyang Xiu.
[an essayist from 11th century]
I'd love to hear your thoughts.
Sir Ouyang Xiu wrote,
"Inferior men become temporary allies only when their interests coincide."
“But are at each other's throats if they vie for first place,
or if they drift apart when the benefits of alliance dwindle.”
An alliance based solely on benefits can easily collapse over benefits.
That being said, no faction should be a concern for Your Majesty.
You always coax me into feeling better.
Reciting Ouyang's essay doesn't count.
You must transcribe the complete essay
so I can see your handwriting when I'm upset.
This whole conversation Your Majesty just
wanted to coax me into copying down an essay.
My handwriting is no better than the script
on a Taoist Fulu to dispel evil spirits.
Your Majesty should ask a famous calligrapher to write it.
Your Majesty ...
The male calligraphers have good writing but bold and rough-hewn.
Unlike a lady's attentive and dainty writing
which can help me calm down and concentrate.
I'm honored to obey if Your Majesty says so.
Please.
Your Highness.
Your Highness, in addition to the 100,000 taels Zhao Zhiyuan promised,
He offered Your Highness some extra gifts.
I didn't expect him to persuade my brother.
Mr Zhao showed absolute loyalty to Great General Nian.
It was unexpected that the Great General would personally ask His Majesty to re-appoint Zhao.
And Zhao only said one sentence to my brother?
Exactly, Your Highness.
Now I'm intrigued.
What could this sentence be?
I heard that when Mr Zhao visited the Great General,
he simply said 300,000 taels would be sent to the Great General
and 100,000 to the Palace of Earthly Honor.
So, he's competent.
My Lady, you put all your heart into this robe.
It is impeccable work.
Lingrong's needlework is ten times better than mine.
There is always someone who has better skills.
But no one could put more thought into it than you.
His Majesty is so good to me.
I must commit all my heart to him.
The finishing touches to a dragon are the eyes.
You are just a few stitches from completion.
Well, it took me a good couple of days.
My Lady, you are so skilled at embroidery.
Even the professional weavers do not compare to you.
And it's a very thoughtful gift, My Lady.
A sleeping robe is worn next to the skin.
His Majesty will be able feel your affection if he wears it.
Your Majesty, Her Majesty the Empress is here.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
The bills of the harem this month have been cleared.
I brought the account book for Your Majesty's review.
How come the Palace of Earthly Honor spent 8,000 taels this month?
That is three times more than your palace.
It is the New Year in one month.
Consort Fleur is fond of an extravagant lifestyle. Her expenditures are not surprising.
Even so, you are the Empress and she is a consort.
Her spending cannot exceed yours.
Consort Fleur wrapped her decorations with gold foil to gain face.
She ordered new clothing and jewelry
from the Household Department.
Besides, General Nian returned to Beijing,
so she had to spend more to reward his servants.
That was why she had additional expenses.
“A woman adorns herself for those who delight her.”
Consort Fleur is also maintaining prestige for the Nians and the Imperial Family.
It's not a big deal if she is doing so for the Nians.
Let me know how much she spends in the future.
Yes.
However, these are just the expenses of her palace.
I have an inkling that she spent even more on the rewards.
I believe Nian Gengyao supported Consort Fleur a lot.
She gets the benefits from the price her family paid.
Let her be.
Excuse my bluntness, Your Majesty,
if the money came from Nian Gengyao,
did you reward him that much?
If not, where could the money come from
to cover her enormous expense in a month?
I'm aware of the discrepency. Let's not pursue it.
Yes.
Your Majesty, sleep robes have arrived from both the Palace of Pearl Jade and the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Please have a look.
The two sisters are mentally synchronized.
Your Majesty should take a look right away.
Bring them forward.
The golden dragon is embroidered so vividly.
This is apparently from Attendant An.
No one in the palace exceeds her at embroidery.
It's good.
She is meticulous about the details even on a sleep robe.
Attendant An seems to always have Your Majesty in her heart.
Chun'er is still like a kid. She is very fond of
body powders and wants to show us her collection.
Why not ?
My instructor always says I need to make my skin brighter and puts so much powder on me.
Now that I have some good powders, I have to show them to you, Sourire.
This is the Jasmine Powder from Yangzhou.
It’s said to be made of ground white jasmine flowers.
The powder is fine and fragrant,
and even whiter than snow.
This is indeed superior powder.
I have a box of Sunflower Powder.
It's white, but not as fragrant as the Jasmine Powder.
I thought it was already a lot of trouble to powder my face.
Now I have to powder every part of my body.
Putting on more powder will make your skin finer.
But it won't make a difference overnight.
You will have to powder yourself every day and every night to make your skin like a peeled egg.
Come here, I'll powder you into a fragrant egg.
An egg His Majesty will absolutely like.
Speaking of His Majesty, when I served him last night,
I was curious to know if his body is fair.
I really wanted to find out.
You know, I never dared to open my eyes.
Stop it, stop your nonsense.
Sourire, don't stop her.
Let her tell us.
She is being coarse. Don't indulge her.
I tried so hard to look...
And His Majesty looked at me and said,
why are you staring at me today?
Do you like the pattern "golden dragon
emerging from clouds" on my robe?
I will have it cut out for you if you like.
And then?
Then His Majesty took off the robe and put on another with "two dragons fighting over a flaming pearl".
His Majesty said to me,
"Don't stare at me anymore. Go to sleep."
So His Majesty put on another robe?
Yes, why would I make that up?
His Majesty added that he really likes the material of the robe with "two dragons fighting over a flaming pearl".
He said it calms him to the heart.
So I asked, "Who made you this robe?"
His Majesty smiled, "Go ask your dear sister Sourire."
Oh, I didn't know it was made by Sourire.
Don't listen to her. I don't believe that!
Those were his exact words!
I asked him, “Do you like this robe in particular because it was made by Sourire?"
He said, “Hmm, clothes made by different people feel different.”
And I laughed, "Do you not like the robe with one dragon because the pattern is conservative?"
"It must be made by the Embroidery Department."
Stop this nonsense.
You must speak with propriety
no matter how much His Majesty likes you.
Hmm, I just felt that the one dragon was lonely in the clouds.
Why doesn't he have a companion?
That's enough. We are not talking about this now.
Don't tell everyone what His Majesty said to you.
My kitchen made plum blossom cakes.
Go check if they are ready.
Get some for Lingrong if they are.
That's great!
Jinxi, go with her.
Let’s go.
The imperial doctor dropped by today.
He said glutinous cakes can cause me indigestion.
It’s almost time for my medicine.
I should go now.
Certainly. Take care, Lingrong.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
What’s wrong, My Lady?
Why are you crying?
Get out.
My Lady misses her family. Don't take it personal.
You can go work outside.
Yes.
Did Chun’er leave?
Yes, she hopped back with two packs of cakes joyfully.
She’s a child at heart and always cheerful.
Of your friends, My Lady,
Companion Shen is gentle and decorous;
Attendant Chun is innocent and pure;
Attendant An has a delicate heart.
Because of that, I’m always cautious about what I say to her.
Chun’er had no ill intention over the robe.
But I’m afraid Lingrong is sensitive about it.
Attendant Chun is unsophisticated and free-spoken.
That is a precious personality in the harem.
But it worries me that she might be too free-spoken.
She doesn't even realize when she offends someone.
My Lady, you have to help them mend their fences.
The Hetian jade on the paired hairpins feels
warm and gentle. It is of rare quality.
Send them to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness for Lingrong.
Um ... I remember this pair of jade hairpins
was a private gift from His Majesty.
My Lady, you are making a great effort
to comfort Attendant An.
Real friends in the palace are rarer than jade.
I don’t wish her to be unhappy.
I will send them to Attendant An with great care.
She will understand your sincere intention, My Lady.
I will take my leave.
Certainly.
Peace to My Lady.
Madam, what brings you here?
Lady Sourire recently received a pair of jade hairpins.
She sees you as her closest sister in the palace,
so she asked me to send the hairpins to you.
I am deeply grateful.
She always remembers me
when she receives a precious gift.
Lady Sourire told me that you two would always share jewelry when you were living with her.
Now, in the palace, she wishes always to
share her joy and happiness with you.
Coua, put it away carefully.
Yes.
I am overjoyed to receive this.
Please thank her profusely on my behalf.
I heard Sourire coughing slightly today.
Madam, may I trouble you to make
loquat leaf tea with rock sugar for her?
Thanks for your concern, My Lady.
I will follow your order.
I have some words to pass on to you, My Lady.
Attendant Chun is young and free-spoken.
Please be forgiving of her if she said anything improper.
We are sisters in the imperial family.
I don't mind Chun'er.
I know the person she is.
My Lady, your tolerance and understanding
means a lot to Attendant Chun.
I shall take my leave.
Take care.
Coua, walk Madam Cui out.
Yes, My Lady.
Take care, Madam.
Daisy?
Why are you standing here on such a freezing day?
Madam...
What happened?
My Lady was crying when she came back.
But when I asked, she smashed the tea cup and sent me out.
I have never seen her so angry.
Every master gets angry at their servants.
Attendant An is one of the most even-tempered.
Stop crying.
Tears can cause chill burns on your face.
What a rarity! The jade on the hairpin
gets warm when you touch it.
But My Lady, why don't you look pleased?
Would you be happy if I awarded it to you?
Of course, My Lady.
Indeed, we feel happy when we are rewarded.
But she and I, we are both His Majesty's concubines.
I have never even seen such nice hairpins.
But she has too many.
So when she knew I was upset, she could easily reward me with this.
Don't overthink, My Lady.
I don't want to overthink.
When she received good fabric,
she rewarded me two pieces at her pleasure.
When we made sleep robes for His Majesty,
her robe was more comfortable,
while mine was cut up into a gift.
And now, even Attendant Chun can "climb on top of me".
She said my embroidery was conservative ...
and unpresentable....
and cursed me to be lonely like the dragon.
Attendant Chun is young and newly in favor.
It's understandable that she makes flippant remarks.
My Lady, please don't take her seriously.
Lady Sourire cares a lot about you.
She sent you the jade hairpins.
She didn't send them for me.
She sent them to me because she doesn't want bad feelings between me and Attendant Chun.
Attendant Chun said they are close
because they had similar family backgrounds.
What am I compared to them?
Lady Sourire sent me this to protect Attendant Chun.
Otherwise, she wouldn't send me such a valuable gift.
If so, Lady Sourire only cares about Attendant Chun.
And when Companion Shen was in favor,
she didn't care about us either.
Now I understand --
she wouldn't help me if Companion Shen
had not fallen from grace.
Now that she has Attendant Chun on her side,
she doesn't need me anymore.
She will leave me behind.
If you are angry about the hairpins, My Lady,
I will put them into storage.
I don't want them to upset you again.
She rewarded me such a valuable gift.
I will wear them nicely.
Otherwise, the hairpins just go to waste.
By the way, you saw Jinxi talking to Daisy?
Yes, they were chatty and cordial.
Now I know,
were it not for Daisy,
Lady Sourire wouldn't have coincidentally made a robe for His Majesty
to compete for his favor.
My Lady, you must be vigilant about Daisy in the future.
Why is Your Majesty wearing this old robe tonight?
Lady Sourire and Attendant An
have sent in new robes to Your Majesty.
An older robe feels more comfortable.
Wearing it next to the skin brings my mind peace.
This robe was made by the Empress Première [her sister].
She made quite a few sleep robes for me.
But there are only two left now.
My sister was excellent at needlework.
Time for bed.
All right
Consort Fleur invited all the concubines to
watch operas in the Harmony Theater tomorrow.
Her Majesty the Empress.
Her Highness Consort Fleur.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
All rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
What are we watching today?
Your Majesty, the South Opera House prepared Liu Jinding's "The Emperor's Rescue."
And they can take requests from their opera listing.
Let them begin.
I and Her Majesty will take our time to order.
Yes, Your Highness.
Here is the opera listing, Your Majesty.
I remember they have "Romance of the Three Kingdoms" adapted from "Records of the Three Kingdoms".
What does Your Majesty think?
We will watch it if you like.
Sourire, how can Consort Fleur order before Her Majesty?
It's a good show. You will like it.
I'll choose "Xue Dingshan's Expedition to the West".
Your Highness's brother achieved spectacular feats on the battlefields.
Just like the Great General Xue Dingshan of Tang Dynasty,
who is remembered through the ages.
That's very sweet of you, Lady Cao.
Your Majesty should order a show.
My favorite is the "Persuasion to Good-doing".
I'll order that and "Yaotai".
Your Majesty is like the benevolent Mother Yaotai
who brings blessings to the world.
"The Persuasion to Good-doing" is adapted from the folk story about Mulian rescuing his mother.
[the story condemns rebellion]
The Third Prince is a filial son like Mulian.
Consort Astuce, the Pingjin embroidered hand warmer you are
using was a gift from your son, the Third Prince.
You have a good memory, Consort Fleur.
I hope he has more than just filial piety.
His Majesty would be less upset if the
Third Prince would spend more time on his studies.
Fleur, you look gorgeous in this dress.
The gold and ruby headress also complement your style.
It's a lustrous outfit.
I was afraid that under Jiang Zhongmin's leadership, the
Household Department would be incapable of making good outfits.
I asked my brother to order it from the Treasure House in town.
I still found the gold threads woven a bit too loosely although
I heard it was made tirelessly by over ten senior weavers.
It's just a wee bit finer than what
the Household Department makes.
I'll just have to wear what I have.
Such a luxurious outfit is quite expensive, isn't it?
The price comes second to the quality.
Your Majesty should not always be counting pennies.
It's my duty to carefully manage such a grand household.
I wouldn't mind the price if an outfit can
complement your unrivaled beauty.
I'm really gratified to hear Your Majesty say so.
I heard that Your Majesty tattled on me for my additional spending.
Your Majesty doesn't have to worry over the money I spend.
It's none of your concern.
My family will cover all the additional spending for me.
I'm glad that you are so understanding.
I hope all of you can learn from Consort Fleur that each thread and every stitch is hard-earned.
If you don't have more sources of income,
you can reduce expenditure instead.
I humbly thank Your Majesty.
I will follow your advice.
All right, you may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Speaking of Xue Dingshan's Expedition to the West,
we always think about Fan Lihua.
Look at her!
She makes every effort to please her husband.
But her husband only has another woman in his heart
and declares a divorce three times.
If I were her, I would rather leave him than staying with his loveless body.
A primary wife has to tolerate the concubines.
And the primary wife is the only wife, no matter how much her husband favors the concubines.
Even though Xue Dingshan divorces her three times,
he also pleads three times for her return.
That is all because of her powerful family.
She is the daughter of the primary wife
of a Western Turkic general.
If she was the daughter of a secondary wife,
without "the power to move mountains and seas",
she could not expect anything but death.
Does Your Majesty agree?
Your Majesty, can we also watch the "Dream of Nanke"?
Sourie, that is just about a dream after all the drama.
What's the fun of that?
We watch an opera not only for fun,
but also for the lesson from the story.
"I see his house uprise;
I see his house collapse."
A fall is worse from a more elevated position.
Once his house collapses and his guests are gone,
who would even care about his parentage?
Who would care about wealth and power?
It's all a dream of Nanke.
I appreciate Lady Sourire's reflections on the opera.
No wonder His Majesty enjoys talking to you.
I was simply talking about the story.
I also believe that "the clouds will clear for a bright moon".
What matters is the mutual love between two hearts.
Attendant An, as His Majesty's concubine,
how can you declare "mutual love" openly in public?
It's almost a talent to have such thick skin.
The Peony Pavilion writes,
"Love springs from an unknown origin
and courses deep to an infinite end. "
"It empowers the alive to die,
and revives the dead to life."
Lingrong was just talking about the opera.
Lady Sourire not only is well versed in poetry,
but also can readily draw quotations from operas.
We've been talking about the opera.
Now let's go back to the opera.
Today is the Laba Festival.
[celebration of Buddha's enlightenment]
The entire harem will pay respect to
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager.
We must be ready soon, My Lady.
The fur lining of the coat is so fine and slick.
The Household Department is very thoughtful.
They know you are sensitive to the cold and
picked the best fur lining for you, My Lady.
Well, it stopped snowing and
will get much colder in the following days.
My Lady, this fur coat is warmer and brightly colored.
It's newly offered by the Household Department.
Do you think it's appropriate?
It's a big day for the entire palace.
It's really unnecessary to stand out.
A gentle color complements your modesty.
Her Majesty summons all the concubines.
Lady Sourire, Lady Fuca, and Lady Cao
will bow to Her Majesty.
We wish Your Majesty good health and prolonged happiness.
I haven't seen Lady Sourire for a long time.
Raise your head.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.